Archibald M. Crossley Papers 1999.0007
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
Archibald M. Crossley Papers.
undated, 1926-2002.
1999.0007
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
50.55 Linear feet
The Archibald M. Crossley Papers contains the personal and professional papers of survey research pioneer,. Reports, studies, questionnaires, correspondence and publications document the interactions, interests and activities of Crossley and his peers, as well as the polling organizations and companies with which he was associated.
Crossley, Archibald M.
Biography
Archibald Maddock Crossley was born 7 December 1896 in Fieldsboro, New Jersey. An early pioneer of public polling and one of the first to use representative sampling techniques, Crossley was a 1917 graduate of Princeton University. Employed by J. H.Cross Company (1918-1922), a small advertising firm in Philadelphia, he later joined the Literary Digest (1922-1926) as an assistant research director. In 1926, he established his own marketing research company, Crossley, Inc..
His first significant contribution to commercial market research was the creation of a radio audience measurement system, "Crossley Ratings," in 1929. The ratings determined the audience size of radio broadcasts by calling homes and asking people what they listened to the previous night or day segment. The first to methodically measure local and national audiences by telephone on a systematic basis, Crossley is credited with originationg the term "rating." Crossley ratings were followed with the simpler "Hooper Ratings" in 1946. Even now, ratings are the basis for advertising costs and program renewals. Crossley also played a major role in research on printed media through the "Continuing Study of Magazine Audiences" (CSMA) and studies for Life, Look and other publications. The Crossley agency became an almost indispensible business aid for newspapers, magazines, advertising agencies and broadcasting firms, becoming one of the first to sample public reaction to brand names of breakfast foods, toothpaste, soap, silver and other household items.
In 1936 Crossley competed with two other survey research pioneers, George Gallup and Elmo Roper, to successfully predict the results of the United States Presidential election. The 1936 election was a pivotal point in polling after the Literary Digest incorrectly predicted the defeat of Franklin D. Roosevelt, demonstrating the fallibility of polls based on sheer numbers and the merit of polls based on scientifically selected samples of the U.S. population. Crossley, Inc. merged with the market research firm of Stewart, Dougall & Associates to form Crossley SD Surveys in 1954, later a subsidiary of Westat, Inc. Crossley himself continued doing political research as a consultant through ArchCross Associates, including several studies for Governor Nelson Rockefeller of New York.
Concerned with ethics in polling, Crossley was a founder of the Market Research Council, and active in the National Council on Public Polls and the American Association for Public Opinion Research of which he was president in 1969. He was awarded the Bok Prize for the first radio ratings by Harvard University (1931), the silver medal for service to radio Advertising Award (1943) and the AAPOR Award for exceptional achievement.
Throughout his career, Crossley "concentrated on the psychology of questionnaires, focusing on how question wording could affect how the intensity of a given response is measured. This led him to crusade for ethics and professional polling standards". [ Encyclopedia of Survey research methods, v. 2, 2008, p. 170.]
Crossley was 88 when he died at his home in Princeton, NJ on 1 May 1985.
Scope and Content
The collection contains the personal and professional papers of survey research pioneer, Archibald M. Crossley. Reports, studies, questionnaires, correspondence and publications document the interactions, interests and activities of Crossley and his peers, as well as the polling organizations and companies with which he was associated including Crossley SD Surveys, Inc., ArchCross Associates, Inc. and Political Surveys and Analyses, Inc. The collection is a rich resource of data regarding American opinions on a variety of products, services and politicians throughout the middle years of the twentieth century.
Arrangement
Series I: Consumer Studies ( undated, 1927-1969 )
Series II: Political Surveys ( undated, 1936-1969 )
Series III: Socio-Economic Surveys ( undated, 1937-1964 )
Series IV: International Tensions [Princeton 1917 Project] ( undated, 1976-1982 )
Series V: Speeches ( undated, 1939-1975 )
Series VI: Correspondence ( undated, 1943-1980 )
Series VII: Business Organizations ( undated, 1926-2002 )
Series VIII: Personal Papers ( undated, 1930-2002 )
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to public polling and survey research. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Separated Material
The following materials have been separated from the collection and cataloged:
Teleskon Dodd Periodicals
Resolving nationality conflicts Dodd C10170
Watch your selling dollar Dodd
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated in several installments by Helen Crossley beginning in 1999.
ArchCross Associates, Inc.; Crossley SD Surveys, Inc.; Crossley, Archibald M.; Crossley, Inc.; Political Surveys and Analyses, Inc.; Administrative Records.; Advertisements.; Books.; Charts (graphic documents).; Contracts.; Correspondence.; Financial Records.; Interviews.; Lawsuits.; Manuscripts.; Maps.; Minutes.; Newsletters.; Newspapers.; Notes.; Photocopies.; Photographs.; Press releases.; Questionnaires.; Speeches.
- Series I: Consumer Studies, undated, 1927-1969
  - Subseries A: Radio, undated, 1927-1950
    - Association of National Advertisers, Inc.--Twin Cities Station Report (analysis only), 1932 November - 1933 July (Box 1:, Folder 1)
    - Broadcast Advertising Bureau, Inc.
      - Listening, Viewing, and Reading Study: Cincinnati, OH, 1952 April (Box 1:, Folder 2)
      - Sources of Awareness of Store Special Sales Study: Munice, IN, 1954 April - May (Box 1:, Folder 3)
      - Sources of Awareness of Store Special Sales Study: Toledo, OH, 1954 April - May (Box 1:, Folder 4)
      - Sources of Awareness of Store Special Sales Study: Denver, CO, 1954 May (Box 1:, Folder 5)
      - Sources of Awareness of Store Special Sales Study: South Bend, IN, 1954 May (Box 1:, Folder 6)
      - Sources of Awareness of Store Special Sales Study, Field Materials, undated (Box 1:, Folder 7)
    - C.B.S.--Listerine Bathroom Inventory Report (analysis only), 1940 February (Box 1:, Folder 8)
    - Connecticut Light and Power--News and Weather Report Audiences Study, 1950 June (Box 1:, Folder 9)
    - Cooperative Analysis of Broadcasting (C.A.B.)
      - History (inception and early years)--Correspondences, 1930 January - 1934 December (Box 1:, Folder 10)
      - History (inception and early years)--Governing Committee and Recommendations for Future Development, undated (Box 1:, Folder 11)
      - History (inception and early years)--Operations, undated (Box 1:, Folder 12)
      - History (inception and early years)--Press Releases, undated (Box 1:, Folder 13)
      - History (inception and early years)--Subscribers and Promotions, undated (Box 1:, Folder 14)
      - Radio Listening Habits Supplemental Report, undated (Box 1:, Folder 15)
      - Radio Listening Habits Report, [1927 November] (Box 1:, Folder 16)
      - Selecting Program Time and Talent for Maximum Audience Study (analysis only), 1930-1934 (Box 1:, Folder 17)
      - Radio Listening Habits Comprehensive Report, 1930 March - June (Box 1:, Folder 18)
      - Cumulative Radio Usage Report, 1930 March - July (Box 1:, Folder 19)
      - Radio Listening Progress Report, 1930 March - August (Box 1:, Folder 20)
      - Radio Listening Habits Comprehensive Report, 1930 March - 1931 February (Box 1:, Folder 21)
      - Radio Listening Habits Comprehensive Report, 1930 July - October (Box 1:, Folder 22)
      - Radio Listening Progress Report, 1930 August - September (Box 1:, Folder 23)
      - Radio Listening Progress Report, 1930 October - November (Box 1:, Folder 24)
      - Radio Listening Progress Report, 1930 November - December (Box 1:, Folder 25)
      - Radio Listening Progress Report, 1930 December - 1931 January (Box 1:, Folder 26)
      - Radio Listening Progress Report, [1931] January - February (Box 1:, Folder 27)
      - Radio Listening Progress Report, [1931] February - April (Box 1:, Folder 28)
      - Radio Listening Habits Comprehensive Report, 1931 March - 1932 February (Box 1:, Folder 29)
      - Radio Listening Progress Report, [1931] April - May (Box 1:, Folder 30)
      - Radio Listening Habits Comprehensive Report, [1931] April - June (Box 1:, Folder 31)
      - Special Advance Report on Remote Towns (analysis only), [1931 June] (Box 1:, Folder 32)
      - Radio Listening Progress Report, 1931 July (Box 1:, Folder 33)
      - Radio Listening Habits Comprehensive Report, [1931] July - October (Box 1:, Folder 34)
      - Radio Listening Progress Report, [1931 August] (Box 1:, Folder 35)
      - Radio Listening Progress Report, [1931] September (Box 1:, Folder 36)
      - Radio Listening Progress Report, 1931 September, November (Box 1:, Folder 37)
      - Radio Listening Progress Report, 1931 October - December (Box 1:, Folder 38)
      - Radio Listening Progress Report, 1931 November - 1932 January (Box 1:, Folder 39)
      - Report of Analysis of the Cooperative Analysis of Broadcasting, 1932 (Box 1:, Folder 40)
      - Radio Listening Habits Comprehensive Report, 1932 March - June (Box 1:, Folder 41)
      - Radio Listening Habits Comprehensive Report, 1932 March - 1933 February (Box 1:, Folder 42)
      - Radio Listening Habits Comprehensive Report, 1932 July - October (Box 1:, Folder 43)
      - Program Report [No. 35], 1932 August (Box 1:, Folder 44)
      - Radio Program Audiences Report, 1933 (Box 1:, Folder 45)
      - Radio Listening Habits Comprehensive Report, 1933 March - June (Box 1:, Folder 46)
      - Radio Listening Habits Comprehensive Report, 1933 March - 1934 February (Box 1:, Folder 47)
      - Radio Listening Habits Comprehensive Report, 1933 July - October (Box 1:, Folder 48)
      - Program Report No. 68, 1934 January (Box 2:, Folder 49)
      - Program Report No. 69, 1934 January (Box 2:, Folder 50)
      - Program Report No. 70, 1934 February (Box 2:, Folder 51)
      - Radio Program Popularity Analysis (formerly: Radio Listening Habits Comprehensive Report), 1934 March - June (Box 2:, Folder 52)
      - Radio Program Popularity Analysis, 1934 March - 1935 February (Box 2:, Folder 53)
      - Program Report Vol. V, No. 4, 1934 April (Box 2:, Folder 54)
      - Radio Program Popularity Analysis, 1934 July - October (Box 2:, Folder 55)
      - Radio Station Popularity Analysis, 1934 September (Box 2:, Folder 56)
      - Program Report Vol. V, No. 15, 1934 October (Box 2:, Folder 57)
      - Program Report Vol. V, No. 16, 1934 October (Box 2:, Folder 58)
      - Comprehensive Analysis of Radio Set Usage, 1934 October - 1935 April (Box 2:, Folder 59)
      - Program Report Vol. V, No. 17, 1934 November (Box 2:, Folder 60)
      - Program Report Vol. V, No. 18, 1934 November (Box 2:, Folder 61)
      - Radio Station Popularity Analysis, 1935 March (Box 2:, Folder 62)
      - Radio Program Popularity Analysis, 1935 March - June (Box 2:, Folder 63)
      - Radio Program Audiences Report, 1935 October - 1936 April (Box 2:, Folder 64)
      - Station Audiences Report, 1935 October - 1936 April (Box 2:, Folder 65)
      - History (middle years)--Correspondences, 1936 May - 1943 December (Box 2:, Folder 66)
      - History (middle years)--Governing Committee and Recommendations for Future Development, undated (Box 2:, Folder 67)
      - History (middle years)--Operations, undated (Box 2:, Folder 68)
      - History (middle years)--Publications, undated (Box 2:, Folder 69)
      - History (middle years)--Subscribers, undated (Box 2:, Folder 70)
      - Radio Program Audiences Report, 1936 May - September (Box 2:, Folder 71)
      - Radio Program Audiences Report, 1936 October - 1937 April (Box 2:, Folder 72)
      - Rural Radio Listening Habits Report, [1937] (Box 2:, Folder 73)
      - Program Audiences and Listening Habits (Rural v. City), 1937 Spring (Box 2:, Folder 74)
      - [Rural] Program Report, [1937] March - April (Box 2:, Folder 75)
      - Radio Program Audiences Report, 1937 May - September (Box 2:, Folder 76)
      - Radio Program Audiences Report, 1937 October - 1938 April (Box 2:, Folder 77)
      - Station Audiences Report, 1937 October - 1938 April (Box 2:, Folder 78)
      - Program Audiences and Listening Habits (Rural v. City), 1938 Spring (Box 2:, Folder 79)
      - Radio Program Audiences Report, 1938 May - September (Box 2:, Folder 80)
      - Radio Program Audiences Report, 1938 October - 1939 April (Box 2:, Folder 81)
      - Program Audiences and Listening Habits (Rural v. City), 1939 Spring (Box 2:, Folder 82)
      - Radio Program Audiences Report, 1939 May - September (Box 2:, Folder 83)
      - Radio Program Audiences Report, 1940 May - September (Box 2:, Folder 84)
      - Radio Program Audiences Report, 1940 October - 1941 April (Box 2:, Folder 85)
      - Radio Program Popularity Report, 1941 (Box 2:, Folder 86)
      - Sponsor Identification Report, 1941 (Box 2:, Folder 87)
      - Program Audiences and Listening Habits (Rural v. City), 1941 Spring (Box 2:, Folder 88)
      - Radio Program Audiences Report, 1941 May - September (Box 2:, Folder 89)
      - Sponsor Identification Report Vol. XII, No.s 16, 18, [1941 October - November] (Box 2:, Folder 90)
      - Radio Program Audiences Report, 1941 October - 1942 April (Box 3:, Folder 91)
      - Radio Program Audiences Report, 1942 May - September (Box 3:, Folder 92)
      - Radio Program Audiences Report, 1942 October - 1943 April (Box 3:, Folder 93)
      - Station Audiences Report, 1942 October - 1943 April (Box 3:, Folder 94)
      - Sponsor Identification Report, 1943 March - May (Box 3:, Folder 95)
      - Radio Program Audiences Report, 1943 May - September (Box 3:, Folder 96)
      - Comprehensive Analysis of Radio Program Audiences, 1943 October - 1944 April (Box 3:, Folder 97)
      - History (final years)--Chronology of the C.A.B., undated (Box 3:, Folder 98)
      - History (final years)--Correspondences, 1944 February - 1947 December (Box 3:, Folder 99)
      - History (final years)--Governing Committee and Recommendations for Future Development, undated (Box 3:, Folder 100)
      - History (final years)--Operations, undated (Box 3:, Folder 101)
      - History (final years)--Press Releases, undated (Box 3:, Folder 102)
      - History (final years)--Publications, undated (Box 3:, Folder 103)
      - Radio Program Popularity Report, 1944 (Box 3:, Folder 104)
      - Set-User Program Report, 1944 March (Box 3:, Folder 105)
      - Comprehensive Analysis of Radio Program Audiences, 1944 Summer (Box 3:, Folder 106)
      - Comprehensive Analysis of Radio Program Audiences, 1944 Fall - Winter (Box 3:, Folder 107)
      - Radio Program Popularity Report, 1945 (Box 3:, Folder 108)
      - Comprehensive Analysis of Radio Program Audiences, 1945 Fall - Winter (Box 3:, Folder 109)
      - Comprehensive Analysis of Radio Set Usage, 1945 Fall - Winter (Box 3:, Folder 110)
      - Program Report Vol. XVI, No. 15, 1945 September - October (Box 3:, Folder 111)
      - Special Program Popularity Report, 1945 September, October (Box 3:, Folder 112)
      - Audience Composition Report Vol. II, No. 4, 1946 Spring (Box 3:, Folder 113)
      - City Report, 1946 March - April (Box 3:, Folder 114)
      - Brand Identification Report Vol. III, No. 12, 1946 June (Box 3:, Folder 115)
      - Program Report Vol. XVII, No. 10, 1946 July (Box 3:, Folder 116)
      - Competition and Collaboration with C.E. Hooper, Inc.--Comparative Reports, undated (Box 3:, Folder 117)
      - Competition and Collaboration with C.E. Hooper, Inc.--Correspondences, 1939 November - 1949 November (Box 3:, Folder 118)
      - Competition and Collaboration with C.E. Hooper, Inc.--Press Releases, undated (Box 3:, Folder 119)
      - Costs and Financing, undated (Box 3:, Folder 120)
      - Current Research Problems and Samplings, undated (Box 3:, Folder 121)
      - Field Instructions and Survey Materials--Instructions and Memorandums, undated (Box 3:, Folder 122)
      - Field Instructions and Survey Materials--Various Tabluation Forms, undated (Box 3:, Folder 123)
      - Methodology--Comparative Survey Methods, undated (Box 3:, Folder 124)
      - Methodology--Correspondences, 1935 March - 1941 January (Box 3:, Folder 125)
      - Methodology--Press Releases, undated (Box 3:, Folder 126)
      - Methodology--Sample Public Survey, undated (Box 3:, Folder 127)
      - Methodology--Special Technique Test Report, undated (Box 3:, Folder 128)
      - Methodology--Various Methodological Studies, undated (Box 3:, Folder 129)
      - Newsletters (for C.A.B. members), undated (Box 3:, Folder 130)
      - Newsletters (for public release), undated (Box 3:, Folder 131)
      - Special Analyses, undated (Box 3:, Folder 132)
      - Crossley Inc.--Press Releases, undated (Box 4:, Folder 133)
    - Crossley Inc.--Promotional Materials, undated (Box 4:, Folder 134)
    - Edward Bernays--Columbian Rope Program Study, 1947 December (Box 4:, Folder 135)
    - Esso Standard Oil Co.--Esso Broadcasts Radio Audience Study, 1949 October (Box 4:, Folder 136)
    - International Broadcasting Co. Limited--Radio Listening Habits in Great Britain Report, 1938 October (Box 4:, Folder 137)
    - International Broadcasting Co. Limited--Radio Listening Habits: London and Home Counties Published Report, 1939 February (Box 4:, Folder 138)
    - International Broadcasting Co. Limited-- Great Britain Study Reference Material, undated (Box 4:, Folder 139)
    - Market Research Corporation of America--Rural Radio Ownership and Use Study Proposal, 1937 September (Box 4:, Folder 140)
    - Marschalk and Pratt Co.--Late Night Radio Listening Habits Study: Detroit, MI, 1945 December (Box 4:, Folder 141)
    - Mobil Gas--Radio Advertising Studies, undated (Box 4:, Folder 142)
    - Mutual Broadcasting System
      - Great Scenes from Great Plays Study (analysis only), 1948 December (Box 4:, Folder 143)
      - World Series Audience Survey, [1948] October (Box 4:, Folder 144)
      - World Series Audience Survey, 1949 October (Box 4:, Folder 145)
      - Radio Listening in Home Town America Study, 1950 April (Box 4:, Folder 146)
      - Radio Listening in Home Town America Study: Kingston, NY, 1950 April (Box 4:, Folder 147)
      - Radio Listening in Home Town America Study: Lufkin, TX, 1950 April (Box 4:, Folder 148)
      - Radio Listening in Home Town America Study: Shamokin, PA, 1950 April (Box 4:, Folder 149)
      - Select Program Audience Survey, 1950 September (Box 4:, Folder 150)
      - World Series Audiences Survey, 1950 October (Box 4:, Folder 151)
      - Wisconsin Rapids Expansion Study, 1950 November (Box 4:, Folder 152)
      - Game of the Day Broadcast Study, 1951 September (Box 4:, Folder 153)
      - World Series Audience Survey, 1951 October (Box 4:, Folder 154)
    - N.W. Ayer and Son, Inc.--Baseball Audience Study Report, 1948 September (Box 4:, Folder 155)
    - National and Columbia Broadcasting Systems--Urban Radio Study (analysis only), 1940 January (Box 4:, Folder 156)
    - National Carbon Co.--Eveready Programs Study Report, 1930 January (Box 4:, Folder 157)
    - National Collegiate Athletic Association--Impact of Television on Football Game Attendance Study, 1948 December (Box 4:, Folder 158)
    - National Collegiate Athletic Association--Impact of Television on Football Game Attendance Study: Reference Materials, undated (Box 4:, Folder 159)
    - Pabst Blue Ribbon Beer Co.--Unidentified Field Materials, undated (Box 4:, Folder 160)
    - Procter and Gamble-- Procter and Gamble Radio Programs Coincidental Study, 1950 January (Box 4:, Folder 161)
    - Station KNX--Drugstore Products Advertising Study Report, 1940 April (Box 4:, Folder 162)
    - Station WARM--Radio Audience Study: Scranton, PA (analysis only), 1948 June - July (Box 4:, Folder 163)
    - Station WGY--Exploring with Crossley Published Report, 1943 March (Box 4:, Folder 164)
    - Station WNBF--Radio Listening Coincidental Study: Binghampton, NY, 1948 November (Box 4:, Folder 165)
    - Station WOR
      - Background Information, undated (Box 4:, Folder 166)
      - Greater NY Radio Listening Study Report (No. 1), 1941 June - July (Box 4:, Folder 167)
      - Station Indices, 1941 June - December (Box 4:, Folder 168)
      - Greater NY Radio Listening Study Report (No. 2), 1941 July - August (Box 4:, Folder 169)
      - Greater NY Radio Listening Study Report (No. 3), 1941 August - September (Box 4:, Folder 170)
      - Greater NY Radio Listening Study Report (No. 4), 1941 September - October (Box 4:, Folder 171)
      - Greater NY Radio Listening Study Report (No. 5), 1941 October - November (Box 4:, Folder 172)
      - Greater NY Radio Listening Study Report (No. 6), 1941 November - December (Box 4:, Folder 173)
      - Special Question Studies, 1941 November - 1945 September (Box 4:, Folder 174)
      - Greater NY Radio Listening Study Report (No. 7), 1941 December - 1942 January (Box 4:, Folder 175)
      - Greater NY Radio Listening Study Report (No. 8), 1942 January - February (Box 4:, Folder 176)
      - Station Indices, 1942 January - 1943 June (Box 4:, Folder 177)
      - Greater NY Radio Listening Study Report (No. 9), 1942 February - March (Box 5:, Folder 178)
      - Small Station Report, 1942 February - March (Box 5:, Folder 179)
      - Greater NY Radio Listening Study Report (No. 10), 1942 March - April (Box 5:, Folder 180)
      - Greater NY Radio Listening Study Report (No. 11), 1942 April - May (Box 5:, Folder 181)
      - Greater NY Radio Listening Study Report (No. 12), 1942 May - June (Box 5:, Folder 182)
      - Greater NY Radio Listening Study Report (No. 13), 1942 June - July (Box 5:, Folder 183)
      - Greater NY Radio Listening Study Report (No. 14), 1942 July - August (Box 5:, Folder 184)
      - Greater NY Radio Listening Study Report (No. 15), 1942 August - September (Box 5:, Folder 185)
      - Greater NY Radio Listening Study Report (No. 16), 1942 September - October (Box 5:, Folder 186)
      - Greater NY Radio Listening Study Report (No. 17), 1942 October - November (Box 5:, Folder 187)
      - Greater NY Radio Listening Study Report (No. 18), 1942 November - December (Box 5:, Folder 188)
      - Greater NY Radio Listening Study Report (No. 19), 1942 December - 1943 January (Box 5:, Folder 189)
      - Greater NY Radio Listening Study Report (No. 20), 1943 January - February (Box 5:, Folder 190)
      - Station Indices, 1943 January - 1944 January (Box 5:, Folder 191)
      - Greater NY Radio Listening Study Report (No. 21), 1943 February - March (Box 5:, Folder 192)
      - Greater NY Radio Listening Study Report (No. 22), 1943 March - April (Box 5:, Folder 193)
      - Greater NY Radio Listening Study Report (No. 23), 1943 April - May (Box 5:, Folder 194)
      - Greater NY Radio Listening Study Report (No. 24), 1943 May - June (Box 5:, Folder 195)
      - Greater NY Radio Listening Study Report (No. 25), 1943 June - July (Box 5:, Folder 196)
      - Greater NY Radio Listening Study Report (No. 26), 1943 July - August (Box 5:, Folder 197)